Finding Aid for F.M. Taylor Papers 1878-1949
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
F.M. Taylor Papers 1878-1949
Taylor, F. M. (Fred Manville), 1855-1932.
Professor at Albion College, later professor of political economy at University of Michigan. Correspondence, manuscript articles and lecture notes largely relating to his interest in economics and political science.
8687 Aa 2
0.8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was transferred over the Graduate Library Special Collections (Donor no. 1278 ) in 1944.
The collection is open for research.
Fred M. Taylor was born July 11, 1855 in Northville, Michigan. He was educated at Northwestern University (A.B., 1876, A.M., 1879), then taught for a time at Winnetka High School. He next moved on to Albion College, becoming a professor of history and politics, and teaching from 1879 to 1892. During this period, Taylor attended the University of Michigan where he received his Ph.D. in 1888.
In 1892, Taylor began teaching economics at the University of Michigan, continuing until his retirement in 1929. He was assistant professor of political economy, 1892-1893; junior professor, 1893-1904; professor, 1904-1920; and professor of economics, 1920-1929.
Taylor's specialty in addition to general economic theory, was currency and banking. He wrote important articles on the topic of the circulation and qualities of monetary standards. He also did work on the relation between money and prices. Taylor's most noteworthy work was the text, Principles of Economics (1911) which went through many editions.
Taylor died August 7, 1932.
The Taylor collection has been arranged into four series: Biographical; Correspondence; Essays and Other Writings; and Miscellaneous. Of most note is the Correspondence series which dates from 1878 to 1932 with a few letters dating to 1949 collected by his colleague Z.C. Dickinson who was engaged in a biographical study of Taylor. The correspondence illustrates the range of Taylor's acquaintances and includes important figures in the study of political economy and economics. Corespondents include Henry Carter Adams, Joseph A. Schumpeter, F.W. Taussig, and Friedrich A. Hayek. A selected list of Taylor's correspondents is appended to this finding aid.
Subjects:
Albion College.; Economics--Study and teaching.; Political science.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Economics.
Contributors:
Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.; Davenport, Herbert Joseph, 1861-1931.; Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951.; Farrell, Margaret C. Taylor.; Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943.; Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Friedrich August), 1899-1992; Hinsdale, B. A. (Burke Aaron), 1837-1900.; James, Edmund J. (Edmund Janes), 1855-1925.; Lasson, Adolf, 1832-1917.; Lowell, A. Lawrence (Abbott Lawrence), 1856-1943.; Means, David MacGregor, 1847-1931.; Morris, George Sylvester, 1840-1889.; Ritchie, David George, 1853-1903.; Schumpeter, Joseph Alois, 1883-1950.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; Seligman, Edwin Robert Anderson, 1861-1939.; Seth, James, 1860-1924.; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Taussig, F. W. (Frank William), 1859-1940.; Wenley, R. M. (Robert Mark), 1861-1929.
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (include biographical sketch by Taylor's daughter Margaret C.T. Farrell) (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1878-1890 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1891 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1892 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1893-1900 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1901-1913 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1914-1922 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1923-1925 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1926-1928 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1931-1949 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence undated (Box 1)
- Essays and other writings
  - Comment on Mr. Ellis' paper (Box 1)
  - Comments on Anderson's social value (Box 1)
  - Credit (Box 1)
  - Currency Reform in the United States (Box 1)
  - Demand Schedules and social Importance essay (Box 1)
  - Equilibrium Theory of Value (Box 1)
  - Kant's Critique of Pure Reason 1880s (Box 1)
  - Labor Theory of Value revised (Box 1)
  - Law of Nature (Box 1)
  - Monometallism circa 1884 (Box 1)
  - Rent Chapter 38 Mimeograph copy under revision (Box 1)
  - Report of the American Economic Association (Box 1)
  - The Russian Experiment, final treatment (Box 1)
  - Shifting and Incidence of taxes (Box 1)
  - Social Value (Box 1)
  - Some notes on the principles governing returns (Box 1)
  - Standard of value, 2 essays (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Newsclippings, articles (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Course test questions, etc (Box 1)
  - Principles of Economics (3rd Printing, 8th Edition) corrections and suggested by economics instructors (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous notebooks, 3 volumes (Box 1)
Selective index of correspondents
Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.
April 26, 1892; April 28, 1892; May 11, 1892; May 24, 1892
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.
June 13, 1882; May 19, 1892; undated
Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.
July 19, 1925
Davenport, Herbert Joseph, 1861-1931.
March 15, 1911; April 4, 1911; April 11, 1911
Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951.
April 26, 1922; May 4, 1922; May 10, 1922
Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943.
September 14, 1891; September 18, 1891
Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Friedrich August), 1899-
October 12, 1923; October 27, 1923; November 13, 1923; May 14, 1924; January 23, 1930; February 17, 1934; March 23, 1934; April 1, 1934; April 21, 1934
Hinsdale, B. A. (Burke Aaron), 1837-1900.
November 29, 1891
James, Edmund J. (Edmund Janes), 1855-1925.
November 14, 1892; December 9, 1892; February 7, 1893
Lasson, Adolf, 1832-1917.
December 28, 1891
Lowell, A. Lawrence (Abbott Lawrence), 1856-1943.
November 23, 1891 (2)
Means, David MacGregor, 1847-1931.
October 14, 1891; October 22, 1891; December 1, 1891; February 24, 1892; January 18, 1892
Morris, George Sylvester, 1840-1889.
March 20, 1888; March 21, 1888; November 10, 1888
Ritchie, David George, 1853-1903.
January 13, 1891
Schumpeter, Joseph Alois, 1883-1950.
March 7, 1914; March 15, 1934; March 1, 1934; March 30, 1934; April 15, 1934 ?; April 19, 1934; May 3, 1934
Schurman, J. G. (Jacob Gould), 1854-1942.
February 1, 1892; October 28, 1892
Seligman, Edmund Robert Anderson, 1861-1939.
August 4, 1906
Seth, James, 1860-1924.
March 3, 1892; June 21, 1892
Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.
August 9, 1925; February 25, 1929; February 26, 1929; April 19, 1929; May 3, 1929
Taussig, F. W. (Frank William), 1859-1940.
April 6, 1898; December 20, 1898, March 16, 1898; October 20, 1898; December 30, 1898; June 27, 1927; July 12, 1927
Wenley, Robert Mark, 1861-1929.
February 23, 1929